なんば
むった
(南波 六太)
＜宇宙飛行士になるために➡
Every astronaut must undergo flight training on the T-38 trainer.
欠かせない ジェット練習機
Ｔ－３８の操縦訓練＞
もうり
＜当然ながら あの毛利さんや
のぐち
ほしで
野口さん 星出さんも通った道だ＞
Naturally, Mohri, Noguchi, and Hoshide have all been through it.
＜テストの点の高い生徒には
高いランクの教官がつく中…＞
While students with higher scores are assigned to higher-ranked instructors...
I ended up with
＜俺についた教官は…
デニール･ヤング＞
Deneil Young.
And I was always at the bottom of the list.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ちなみに ワシは
最低ランクだ｡
やっぱり｡
I knew it.
何せ ワシの操縦に
耐えられる生徒がおらんからな｡
After all, none of the students could endure my flying.
ヒャハハ…｡
ワシに ついて来られるなら
他のヤツの１.５倍➡
If you can keep up with me,
you'll progress 1.5 times faster than everyone else.
早く仕上げてやるぞ！
Finally, I...
《いよいよ 私は…飛ぶんだ！》
get to fly!
It's show time.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ショータイムだ！
I have a really bad feeling about this.
《すげえ ヤな予感…》
It's just obvious that the more you put in your bag
The heavier it gets
The harder I work, the closer I get to my goal
But I'm just not getting there fast enough
I gaze at the night sky but it doesn't calm me down
Now that you've heard how loud my heart's beating
Let's take a trip outside
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of dreams and reality
I'm currently updating the canvas of my dreams
With a glittering universe and a blue earth
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of facades and honesty
I'm currently conversing with the canvas of my dreams
On this orbit of fate
With a fire in my belly
#66 Two Notebooks
きつっ！
It's tight.
ねえ ヤンじい これって
Ｇスーツってやつだよね？
Hey, Mr. Young...
Is this a g-suit?
４Ｇを超える飛行の時に
必要っていう…｡
If you go over 4-g, you need one?
お～う！ウハハッ！
ちゃんと学んでるじゃねえか｡
Sounds like you learned the material.
ついでに 頭のノートに
メモっとけ｡➡
Put that down in the notebook in your head.
そいつを着てなきゃ 頭の血が
足に いっちまうって｡
If you aren't wearing one, blood will go straight from your head to your feet.
ブラックアウトになるってな｡
You'll black out.
おっと…ブラックアウトってのは
失神状態に なるってこった｡
Oh...
"Black out" is the term for passing out.
知ってたか？
Did you know that?
し…知ってるよ｡ていうか
初飛行で着るもんなの？これって｡
I knew.
Is this really necessary for my first flight?
何やってんの？ヤンじい｡
What are you doing, Mr. Young?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)さあ 行くぞ！
Okay.
Let's go.
The other AsCans aren't wearing g-suits.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)他のアスキャンは
Ｇスーツなんて着てない｡➡
必要ないからな｡ウハハッ…｡
They won't need them.
いや ウハハハじゃねえよ｡
必要ないなら➡
Why are you laughing?
If I don't need one, why am I wearing this?
こんな大げさなもの
着なくてもいいんじゃ…｡
You're lucky, Mutta.
ラッキーだな ムッタ｡
そいつを着た 宇宙飛行士は➡
Only a few astronauts get to wear g-suits.
数えるほどしか いねえぞ｡
ちなみに ヒビトも着てる｡
Hibito's one of them.
どうする？脱ぐか？
Well? Taking it off?
まさか！
No way.
I'm sure you read all this...
お勉強して わかってると思うが…
飛行機の状態は 常に➡
But the maintenance crew is to keep the aircraft in constantly perfect condition.
整備士が パーフェクトに
仕上げてくれてる｡➡
だが それでも
飛行前の最終チェックは➡
However, performing the final check is the pilot's responsibility.
パイロットが
責任を持ってやるんだ｡
まずは 外回りのチェックだ｡
ちょっと これ持っててくれ｡
First, you check the outside.
Hold this for me.
Huh?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ど～れ｡
Let's see.
《いや 何のための杖だよ！➡
So what is this cane for?
何か…相変わらず
信用ならねえ じいさんだ》
I can't bring myself to trust this old man.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)あ～ よっこらせ！
Oof.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)ムッタも機体チェックしろ｡
お前の頭のノートには➡
Mutta, check the plane.
I'm sure the notebook in your head has the list of places to check.
チェック箇所の情報も
書いてあるんだろ？
当然！フフフ…｡
You bet.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)飛行前のチェック作業は
気を抜くな ムッタ｡➡
When checking an aircraft, never cut corners.
事故った時 整備士に
責任を押しつけるのは➡
The worst thing a pilot can do is crash and get his maintenance crew in trouble.
パイロットの恥っちゅうもんだ｡
今のは 心のノートにメモっとけ｡
Put that in the notebook in your heart.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)メモる場所を間違えるなよ
ムッタ！ウハハハ！
Make sure to use the correct notebook, Mutta.
《ヤベえ…ついに
飛ぶ時が来た！➡
Oh, boy...
I finally get to fly!
そらんちゅ
今日から俺も 空人の
仲間入りに…》
Today is the day I will become a flyboy.
Flyboy
《いや…でも何だろう？
このミョーな不安感は｡➡
Yeah, I've still got a bad feeling about this...
あ～しまった！こんなことなら
飛ぶ前に アマンティに➡
Crap.
I should have asked Amanti to read my fortune first.
みてもらえばよかった！》
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)さあ 今日の旅を
始めよう！
Well, let's get this flight underway!
《いや ちょっと 待って～!!》
Er, wait! Hold on!
ショータイムだ！ウハハッ！
It's show time!
ア…ウッ…｡
ひびと
(南波 日々人)ハァ ハァ…｡
あ～…デニールだな ありゃ｡
That's gotta be Deneil.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)ほんとだ｡いらないのに
スモークまで出してる｡➡
Yeah, he's even releasing smoke for no reason.
ようしゃ
容赦ないなぁ
あのスピード｡
No mercy for the newbie, huh?
６.５Ｇは いってるね｡
He's gotta be pulling 6.5 g.
う～ん…ぐっ….
この…クソじじい！
D-Damn you, old man!
ウエッ…
ゲエッ！
う～…う～｡
《チキショー！いきなり
アクロバｯト飛行 始めやがって｡➡
Jeez...
He was starting me with aerobatics?
まだ 目がグワングワン
回ってる…｡ウエー！》
My head is still spinning...
いいか ムッタ｡初めて
ワシと同乗したヤツは➡
Guess what, Mutta?
Everyone throws up after their first flight with me.
必ず吐く｡ウハハ！
頭のノートに メモっとけ｡
Put that down in the notebook in your head.
そういうことは 先に言ってくれよ｡
You should have warned me earlier.
のっけから これじゃ
もたねえよ｡
This start is too hard for me.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)おう 弱音か？
Oh? Whining already?
今日は もう
やめてもいいぞ｡
I'm willing to call it a day.
ちなみに ヒビトは…｡
I should say that after Hibito's first flight...
⦅ウエー！あ…⦆
⦅ブッ！⦆
⦅ヤンじい…もう一回！⦆
Mr. Young...
One more time!
吐いたあとに
うれしそうな顔しながら➡
After throwing up, he looked up, smiling, and asked to go up again.
｢もっかい乗せろ｣と
言ってきたぞ｡
心のノートに メモっとけ｡
Put that down in the notebook in your heart.
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)さあ どうするムッタ？
止まるも進むも➡
So what will you do, Mutta?
You're the one who must stop, advance, or take control.
コントロールするのは お前だ！
おう！大丈夫か？
そんなフラフラで｡
Hey, sure you can manage on those wobbly legs?
It's a piece of cake!
(ｼｬﾛﾝの声)ムッタへ 飛行機の
訓練は どうですか？➡
Dear Mutta...
How is flight training going?
気持ちいいでしょうね｡きっと
楽しんでることでしょう｡➡
It must feel wonderful.
I'm sure you're having fun.
窓から見える景色なんて
それは最高でしょう｡
The view up there must be gorgeous.
シャロンへ｡当機は現在
目隠し飛行なる➡
Dear Sharon...
Currently,
I am simulating the absurd situation of flying while blindfolded,
じょうき
常軌を逸した訓練が
かんこう
敢行されており➡
正直 真っ暗です｡
景色は一切見えません！
so it's completely dark in here.
I can't see a thing.
C-Crap.
《ヤ…ヤバイ！今 この機体
上下どっち向いてんだ？》
I can't tell which way is up.
オーイ ムッタ！海パンでも
はいてきたのか？お？
Hey, Mutta?
Wearing your swimming trunks?
Huh?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)鼻が下向いてるぞ｡➡
The nose is pointing down.
このままシーズン前に
２人で海水浴始める気か？
It's a little early to swim in the ocean.
う～わっ！やっべぇ!!
Oh, crap!
怖えぇ！
速度計ばっか気をとられて➡
Scary!
I was so focused on the airspeed indicator, I lost track of my altitude and my attitude!
姿勢と高度に
目がいってなかった！
景色はどうせ見えねえんだ｡計器に
だけ注目しろよ ムッタ｡ハハハ！
You can't see anything outside!
Focus on your instruments, Mutta!
見てみろ｡前方に２機の飛行機が
並んで飛んでるだろ｡➡
Look at the screen.
See the two planes flying up ahead?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)他のアスキャン訓練機だ｡
間をブチ抜いて行け！
Yeah.
Those are AsCan trainers.
Fly through them!
What?
はぁ!?え～ ちょっとマジかよ!?
Wait, are you serious?
そういうのは
見えてる時にやらない？
Shouldn't I wait until I can see outside before I try that?
ヘヘヘヘ わかるぜ ムッタ｡➡
I know how you feel, Mutta.
完全に機械の表示のみに命を
ゆだねんのが怖いって気持ちはな｡
It can be scary to have your life ride on a bunch of screens.
だが こういう状況で 計器より
自分の勘に頼ろうとする奴は➡
But in this situation, it's more dangerous to disregard the instruments and follow your instincts.
逆に危険だ｡焦ってる時の勘ほど
狂いやすいものはない｡➡
When you panic, instinct isn't worth a damn.
それで何人のパイロットが➡
As a result of doing that, too many pilots have crashed, victims of vertigo.
おちい
バーティゴに陥って
事故死したことか｡➡
あ～ おっと
バーティゴってのはな 飛行中に➡
Oh, "vertigo" refers to when you suffer spatial disorientation and subsequent panic.
平衡感覚を失ってパニくることだ｡
ハハハ 知ってるな｡
I'm sure you knew that.
こんな時に よくしゃべる｡
集中のジャマだ!!
Why does he have to talk so much?
I can't concentrate!
特に 濃い霧の中とか雲の中とかな
バーティゴに陥りやすいﾎﾟｲﾝﾄだ｡➡
Vertigo is more likely to affect you when you fly through dense fog or clouds.
水平線が見えないと 機体の姿勢や
上下がわからなくなりやすいんだ｡
If you can't see the horizon,
you lose track of which way is up and which is down.
Put that down in the notebook in your head.
メモっとけよ｡頭のノートだ｡
こんなの無理だ！接触する!!
This is impossible.
I'm gonna hit them.
It won't work!
あ～ ダメだ！
Huh?
(ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ)お!?なんだよ ムッタ｡
おじけづいたか？
What's this, Mutta?
Were you scared?
《チクショー！
あれで もし事故ってたら➡
Damn...
What if I caused an accident?
どうする気だったんだ｡
ヤンじいめ》
Stupid Mr. Young...
ナイスフライトだ マックス｡
ハハハ…最高だよ お前｡よしよし｡
Nice flight, Max.
You rule... That's a good boy.
ビビるな ムッタ｡外の景色が
見えなくても こいつはちゃんと➡
Don't be scared, Mutta.
This baby will always move the way you tell it, even if you can't see outside.
ワシらの操縦通りに動く｡
もうちょいマシンを信頼してやれ｡
You have to learn to trust the machine.
It's like the way you trust elevators.
普段乗ってるエレベーター
なんかと同じぐらいな｡
休憩～！
Break time!
Flying through the sky must feel good.
空は気持ちいいでしょうね…｡
《シャロンから手紙が届いた｡➡
I received a letter from Sharon...
電子メールなら一瞬だというのに
手書きの手紙をよこしてきた》
E-mail would have been much faster,
but she sent a hand-written letter.
何でさ 歩けるのに杖ついたり
車イスに乗ったりしてんの？
So...
If you can walk, why use a cane and wheelchair?
Huh?
I don't see a problem.
まあ…
歩けるなら不要なもんだし｡
Well, you shouldn't need those if you can walk.
《いつか本当に歩けなくなる
シャロンのことを考えたら➡
When I think about Sharon being unable to walk soon,
ヤンじいは
ふざけてるようにしか見えん》
Mr. Young seems like he's just fooling around.
ムッタは 遺伝ってやつを
どれくらい信じてる？
Mutta, when it comes to genes, are you a believer?
え？遺伝!?
Huh?
Genes?
(南波父)ニャンボ！ニャンボ！
ニャンボ！ニャンボ！
The wind...
西からワッショイ
The wind goes hey-ho.
Hey-ho from the west...
Hey-ho like the wind!
ニャンボ！
I'm hoping those genes won't stick.
できる限りは 遺伝
信じたくはないな｡
うん｡ワシの親父も祖父もな
ホットドッグが大好物だった｡
My father and grandfather both loved hot dogs.
Both were fat and my height.
ワシと同じように太ってて
身長も同じだった｡
何より飛行機やﾛｹｯﾄが大好きな
ところまで同じときてる｡➡
And they also loved planes and rockets.
こりゃもう滑走路のごとく
一直線な遺伝だ｡
I'd say their genes passed straight to me.
そんな親父も じいさんも
晩年に脚を悪くしてな｡
And toward the end of their lives, both of them had leg issues.
だからワシもそのうち 悪くなるん
だろうなと思ってる訳だ｡ハハハ！
So I expect that my legs will stop working.
杖の使い方もバギーの操作も➡
My plan is to train with a cane and wheelchair ahead of time.
今のうちにバッチリ訓練しとこう
という作戦だ｡
ハハハ…楽しいもんだぜ｡
It's pretty fun!
《訓練…か》
To train, huh...
(ケンジ)ムッくん 訓練の予約？
Mu...
Signing up for training?
Yeah.
ああ 早く入れねえと
埋まっちまうからな｡
If I don't move fast, there won't be any openings.
(せりか)ふ～っ 楽しかったな｡
That was fun...
No, Mutta...
違うぞ ムッタ｡
今んとこギュイーンじゃねえ！➡
You're not supposed to go "whoosh."
ンギュイイイーンだ！
You're supposed to go "whooooooo"!
うるせっ！
Shove it!
Train hard, Mutta.
訓練 頑張ってね ムッタ｡
ンギュイイイーン!!
Whooooooo!
I'm writing letters to train myself.
(ｼｬﾛﾝの声)私も今 訓練のつもりで
手紙を書いてます｡➡
まるで砂利の上で書いたような
ひどい文字ですが…｡➡
But it looks like I wrote this on sand.
訓練を重ねて うまく筆記できる
ようになった例もあると➡
After Serika told me that in some cases, training led to better handwriting, I'm feeling optimistic.
せりかさんから聞いて
ふく
希望が膨らんでいるところです｡➡
これからちょくちょく ヒビトと
ムッタに手紙を書きます｡➡
I'll be writing letters to you and Hibito from time to time.
私の文字が上達していく様を
どうぞ見届けて下さい｡
I hope you'll get to see my handwriting improve.
I wonder how many hours she spent writing this.
《これを書くのに…
何時間かかったんだろ》
Hey, Mr. Young?
なあ ヤンじい｡コントロールが
きかないこともあるよな｡
Isn't it possible that the controls will stop responding?
遺伝で脚が動かなくなったり➡
Then it's possible your legs will stop working due to genes,
or you could be stricken suddenly by an incurable disease...
不治の難病に
突然かかる可能性もあるよな｡
避けようのないもんは
そりゃある｡➡
Some things can't be prevented.
The last of which is death.
さい
その最たるもんが 死だろ｡
格納庫に穴のあいた
Ｔ-３８があったろ｡
Remember the T-38, in the hangar, that had a hole?
I was the one flying it.
あいつもワシが乗ってたんだ｡
コントロールにミスはなかった｡➡
There weren't any mistakes on my part.
I was flying at normal speed and attitude.
あの日もワシは いつもの高度を
いつもの速度で飛んどったんだ｡
⦅ん？…おおっ!!⦆
そいつが鳥だとわかった瞬間には
もう ぶつかってた｡➡
I didn't realize it was a bird until I'd hit it.
かわいそうなことをした｡➡
I felt pretty bad...
If I could have, I'd have avoided it.
ワシだって当然
避けられるもんなら避けてるぜ｡➡
だが それを言ってどうなる｡
But there's no point in saying that now.
ワシらは死ぬまで生きるだけだ｡➡
All we can do is live until the day we die.
コントロールできるかぎり…➡
Control what we can...
自由に飛び回るだけだ！
And fly free!
It's been so long since I looked up at the moon
Though it's always keeping a cold eye on me
Yeah, it always keeps a cold eye on me
I wanna rough up this rotten way home
But even it makes me mad
I can't take my eyes off. Yeah, I can't take my eyes of it
I can't take my eyes off that dazzling smile
What did I want back then?
What was I looking for?
I should've known my tears would take me to my dreams
Blow this gloomy reality away for me
I want to see how tiny our huge worries seem
From up in that dark ocean of space
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#67 Deneil-ized
Hey, what should we have for lunch, Mutta?
＜なあ 昼メシ 何食うよ ムッタ＞
＜黙ってて！＞
Can't you shut up?!
＜この男 空の上で
しゃべ
喋りまくる｡チクショー＞
This guy won't stop talking when I'm flying!
Training with Deneil is more fun once you're Deneil-ized.
＜デニールとの訓練は
ﾃﾞﾆｰﾙ化してからが楽しいんだ＞
＜何だ？それ＞
What's that mean?
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Deneil-ized"
きみ
ぼく
なに
ことば
解かるよ
なんて言葉